REMINISCENCE
STOP
（阿良々木）あっ！
Hachikuji Mayoi
Animation Number 22
（八九寺(はちくじ)）んん…
Hachikuji!
（阿良々木）はっちくじ〜！
It's been so long!
（阿良々木）
久しぶりじゃねえか この！
ハハハハッ
かわいいなあ かわいいなあ！
You're so damn cute!
Let me touch you! Let me hug you!
（阿良々木）
もっと触らせろ
もっと抱きつかせろ！
Ooh, I'm gonna see your panties!
（阿良々木）
パンツ見ちゃうぞ
この この この〜！
X-Ray image
Even closer
Oww!
（阿良々木）
痛(いて)え！ 何すんだ こいつ！
The hell are you doing?!
（八九寺）がう！
わあ〜！
がう！
だっ 大丈夫 大丈夫
敵じゃないぞ
Don't worry, I'm not an enemy!
シャー！
Calm down! Take a deep breath!
ほら 落ち着いて
ゆっくりと呼吸して
フシャー！
コーホー
You breathe like a Terminator.
ロボ超人みたいな呼吸音だな
Araragi's inner thoughts/grumbling
Animation Number 47
It's me! Me! Take a good look!
（阿良々木）
僕だ 僕だぞ　よく見ろ
Oh, it's Muraragi-san.
Muraragi-san
Animation Number 52
むらら木(ぎ)さん
じゃないですか
Don't call people things that sound so unsatisfying.
人のことを
欲求不満みたいな名前で呼ぶな
Sorry, I stuttered.
失礼　かみました
No, you did it on purpose.
違う わざとだ
I bit my tongue!
かみまみた
It wasn't on purpose?!
（阿良々木）わざとじゃない？
God is with us.
神は いた
Animation number 58
Ga~n
What miracle happened to you?!
Animation number 58
Ga~n
（阿良々木）
どんな奇跡体験を！
Animation number 58
Ga~n
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Black Scene
So you've been studying for your exams?
（八九寺）
なるほど　受験勉強ですか
Well, I can get help from the valedictorian and the 7th-best.
（阿良々木）
学年１位と学年７位に
勉強を教えてもらえるからな
Honestly, I'm invincible.
はっきり言って無敵だぜ
White Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Hanekawa-san's the one with braids that I met, right?
（八九寺）
羽川(はねかわ)さん…
は… この間 私もお会いした
あの三つ編みの方ですよね
Yeah.
（阿良々木）そうそう
And Senjougahara-san's your girlfriend.
そして 戦場ヶ原(せんじょうがはら)さんのほうが
阿良々木さんの彼女さん
Yeah.
（阿良々木）だ…
ふうむ
Got a problem with that?
（阿良々木）
何だよ　それが どうかしたか？
I figured you'd go for Hanekawa-san between the two of them.
いや 普通 あの２人だったら
羽川さんのほうを
選ぶんじゃないかと思いまして
It seems kind of weird that you'd pick Senjougahara-san.
どうして戦場ヶ原さんなのか
ふと 不思議に思ってしまいました
Why I'd...
（阿良々木）どうしてって…
I don't think of Hanekawa like that.
羽川は僕にとって
そういう対象じゃないからな
I owe her too much, and she'd probably shoot me down anyway.
あいつは恩人なんだよ
羽川のほうだって
僕なんか願い下げだろうし
Plus I'm into Senjougahara, despite her personality.
それに そもそも
僕は あの性格を含めて
戦場ヶ原のことが…
Well, if you say you prefer Senjougahara-san,
まあ 戦場ヶ原さんのほうがいいと
阿良々木さんが
おっしゃるのでしたら
I guess that's right. It takes all kinds.
それは そうなのでしょう
人の好みは
“選別差別”という話です
Separately discriminated
Animation Number 77
I guess.
It's "everyone has a type", isn't it?
Distinctively separated
Animation Number 78
（阿良々木）
千差万別だろ
By the way, Araragi.
Back to the topic
Animation Number 79
（八九寺）
時に 阿良々木さん
About that vampire.
あの女吸血鬼さん
Um... She's going by Oshino Shinobu-san now, right?
え〜っと 今は忍野忍(おしのしのぶ)さんと
おっしゃるんでしたっけ？
Looks about eight, blonde, with a helmet and goggles?
（八九寺）８歳児くらいで 金髪で
ヘルメットにゴーグル…
でしたよね
（阿良々木）
うん それが どうした？
What about her?
I wasn't able to get close so I can't be sure,
（八九寺）
直接 お会いしたことがないので
確実に断ずることはできませんが
but I think I saw her around yesterday.
昨日 その忍さんを
お見かけしたのですが
（阿良々木）え？
At around five at night,
（八九寺）
夕方の５時頃
国道沿いのドーナツ屋さんのそばに
at the donut shop by the highway.
お一人で いました
Donuts, huh.
（阿良々木）ドーナツ屋ねえ
Would Oshino really let her go out alone like that?
けれど あの忍野が
果たして 忍に単独行動を許すか…
Yeah, I thought the same thing.
（八九寺）
ええ　私も そう思いまして
I thought I should tell you, so I waited for you here.
ご報告しておいたほうが
よいのではと
阿良々木さんを待ち伏せていた
というわけなのです
（阿良々木）あ… そうなの？
Really? Why didn't you say so sooner?
それならそうと最初に言えよ
I'm sorry.
（八九寺）申し訳ありません
Some pedo came up to me and started groping me.
どこかのロリコンが
突然 抱きついてきたため
I was so shocked that I forgot all about it.
ショックで すっかり
忘れてしまっていました
Oh, really? Sorry I gave you the wrong idea.
や〜 そっか
（阿良々木）
わざわざ気を回してもらって
悪かったな
I'm just glad I could help you out.
（八九寺）
阿良々木さんのお役に立てて
何よりです
Anyway, do you have the time?
それより お時間は よいのですか？
Oh, right.
（阿良々木）ああ そうだ
Later, Hachikuji.
じゃ 八九寺　またな
Sure. I know we'll meet again.
はい　また お会いできると
確信しております
エヘッ
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
koishikute
You’re dear to me;
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
itoshikute
I long for you;
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
FIGURE
TRI
ANGLE
Yeah
tomaranai
I can’t stop.
Yeah
After I graduate, I'm going to travel.
semete kono kokoro wa
At least this heart of mine
After I graduate, I'm going to travel.
PHOTOGRAPHIC VERSION
kimi no moto e
Will go to where you are.
Days and months are travellers of eternity. So are the years that pass by.
United Arab Emirates
kimi ga omou hodo
I’m not as much of an angel
Papua/New Guinea
tenshi ja nai kara
As you think I am.
New Zealand
kirameku kimochi ｗa
These shining feelings
FIGURE
Spirits of mountains and streams
chimimouryou
Are really evil spirits.
FIGURE
Spirits of mountains and streams
Be prudent.
Animation number 12
Tsubasa
Argentina
isso no koto mou
At this point, I may as well.
Romania
Bakemonogatari Photographic OP
akuma ni naretara
What if I become a demon?
Portugal
tsubuyaku kotoba wa
The whispered words
FIGURE
Meaning unclear
imi mourou
Have a hazy meaning.
FIGURE
Meaning unclear
ano hi no mama de zutto matteru
Just like I did on that day, I keep on waiting.
akirameta mama ima mo matteru no
I’ve given up, and I’m waiting even now.
iitakute
I want to say it;
ienakute
I can’t say it;
todokanai
It won’t reach,
konna soba ni ite mo
Even though I’m so close to you.
nee dou sureba ii no
Hey, what should I do?
Be prudent.
koishikute
You’re dear to me;
itoshikute
I long for you;
tomaranai
I can’t stop.
semete kono kokoro wa
At least this heart of mine
kimi no moto e
Will go to where you are.
Animation number 24
Tsubasa
Hanekawa Tsubasa
Animation number 26
Tsubasa
BODY
Animation number 28
Tsubasa
Over
They were cat ears.
From the small head of Hanekawa
grew cute cat ears.
I stood silent, biting my lower lip.
So hard it started bleeding.
That's fun
I just decided to be serious,
so I can't smile...
Delivering an appealing speech
which moves your partner
and then bursting with laughter on him,
a typical manga cliche.
Delivering an appealing speech
which moves your partner
and then bursting with laughter on him,
a typical manga cliche.
Delivering an appealing speech
which moves your partner
and then bursting with laughter on him,
a typical manga cliche.
Delivering an appealing speech
which moves your partner
and then bursting with laughter on him,
a typical manga cliche.
Delivering an appealing speech
which moves your partner
and then bursting with laughter on him,
a typical manga cliche.
Delivering an appealing speech
which moves your partner
and then bursting with laughter on him,
a typical manga cliche.
Delivering an appealing speech
which moves your partner
and then bursting with laughter on him,
a typical manga cliche.
Delivering an appealing speech
which moves your partner
and then bursting with laughter on him,
a typical manga cliche.
Delivering an appealing speech
which moves your partner
and then bursting with laughter on him,
a typical manga cliche.
Delivering an appealing speech
which moves your partner
and then bursting with laughter on him,
a typical manga cliche.
Delivering an appealing speech
which moves your partner
and then bursting with laughter on him,
a typical manga cliche.
Delivering an appealing speech
which moves your partner
and then bursting with laughter on him,
a typical manga cliche.
But I swear that at least
I will never do something like that...
Still, these cat ears...
They suit Hanekawa really well,
as if they were specially designed
to match her properly brushed forelock.
They suit Hanekawa really well,
as if they were specially designed
to match her properly brushed forelock.
They suit Hanekawa really well,
as if they were specially designed
to match her properly brushed forelock.
They suit Hanekawa really well,
as if they were specially designed
to match her properly brushed forelock.
They suit Hanekawa really well,
as if they were specially designed
to match her properly brushed forelock.
They suit Hanekawa really well,
as if they were specially designed
to match her properly brushed forelock.
They suit Hanekawa really well,
as if they were specially designed
to match her properly brushed forelock.
They suit Hanekawa really well,
as if they were specially designed
to match her properly brushed forelock.
I thought that during the Golden Week too
You can say she
was born to have cat ears...
If anything.
During the nightmare case
that was the Golden Week,
her ears weren't really Hanekawa-style.
...Thus this immense
destructive power.
Subordinate
Gym
Ah, I see. This time the cat ears are black ,
the same color as her hair.
Typeface used for images: HGP mincho B
Tsubasa Cat, Part Three
Episode 13
Bicycle parking
Gymnasium
New email
Hanekawa Tsubasa
1 new
Oh my.
（戦場ヶ原）あら…
（阿良々木）あっ
Where are you going, Araragi-kun?
阿良々木くん どこかに行くの？
Not far.
ちょっと そこまで
What are you going to do?
（戦場ヶ原）何を しに行くの？
Volunteering.
（阿良々木）人道支援
あらそう いいわ
I see.
Very well. Go ahead, Araragi-kun.
いってらっしゃい 阿良々木くん
I'll take pity on you and answer roll call for you.
特別に情けをかけて
私が代返しておいてあげる
Do it for me?
代返？
I'll say it in your voice, so it should be fine.
ちゃんと阿良々木くんの声色を
使うから大丈夫よ
Leave it to me.
任せておいて
A
Voice Actress/Chiwa Saitou
(Works for Aim Enterprise)
Born in Saitama Prefecture. Voices strong-willed women,
weak women, lively girls and even boys.
Played animals, non-human characters,
eccentric guys speaking in low voice,
and other types of characters too.
Animation Number 79
My voice actress is excellent.
私の声を担当している声優さんは
優秀なのよ
（阿良々木）なっ 声優？
Voice actress?!
What is this, an anime?!
この世界ってアニメだったの？
You're so beautiful, Hitagi-san.
（戦場ヶ原:低い声で）
“ひたぎさん…
なんて美しいんだ”
The woman I've always dreamed of. I love you.
“まさに僕の理想の人だよ”
“愛してる”
How was it? Pretty good?
どう 似てた？
Not even close! I'd been looking forward to it, but it doesn't even match what I imagined!
（阿良々木）似てねえよ！
ちょっと期待しちゃったけど
思いのほか 似てなかったよ！
I haven't even said anything like that yet!
そもそも まだ言ってねえだろがよ
そんなセリフ！
"Yet". So you plan on it in the future?
“まだ”ということは
これから 予定があるのかしら
Yeah!
ある！
Rouhaku Park
Hey, Hanekawa!
（阿良々木）おい 羽川！
（羽川）あっ 阿良々木くん
Araragi-kun!
ハア
You're not supposed to ride your bike in the park.
（羽川）
ダメじゃない
自転車で公園に乗り込んできたら
There's parking for it.
ちゃんと駐輪場があるんだから
This is no time to worry about that!
そんなことを
言ってる場合じゃないだろうが
We're skipping school, quit worrying about biking.
大体 学校サボらせといて
今更 自転車のことなんて…
They're completely different problems.
それとこれとは問題が別よ
Just hurry up and stop.
早く止めてくる
（阿良々木）な…
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Sorry to make you skip school, Araragi-kun.
（羽川）
ごめんね 阿良々木くん
学校 サボらせちゃって
No problem.
（阿良々木）ああ いや 別に
Did you think I was angry? I wasn't trying to be sarcastic.
そんなふうに聞こえちゃったか？
皮肉で言ったわけじゃないよ
Don't worry, I planned it all out.
でも 心配しないで
ちゃんと計算してるから
Naoetsu High School Third Year Timetable
You won't have any trouble being absent from today's classes.
今日の時間割りなら欠席しても
阿良々木くん 何の問題もないから
Unpleasant calculations
Animation Number 157
But what's going to happen to the preparations for the arts festival with the organizers gone?
（阿良々木）
でも 委員長と副委員長が
抜けちまって
文化祭の準備は どうするんだ？
I'm having Senjougahara-san take care of things after school.
（羽川）
放課後の指揮は戦場ヶ原さんに
執ってもらうように しておいたわ
え？
それはミステイクじゃねえのか？
Isn't that a mistake?
She took yesterday off.
戦場ヶ原さん 昨日サボったからね
So it's only fair.
その埋め合わせよ
は〜ん…
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
These have to be her pajamas.
（阿良々木）
しかし これって
どう見てもパジャマだよな
Hey, Hanekawa.
（阿良々木）なあ 羽川
なに？
What?
No, Hanekawa-sama.
（阿良々木）いや 羽川様
Sama?
さま？
Let me take your shirt.
（阿良々木）
上着を こちらで
お預かりいたします
Araragi-kun.
阿良々木くん
Yes?
（阿良々木）はい
You're making me angry.
（羽川）怒るよ
Sorry.
（阿良々木）ごめんなさい
Okay, I'm done joking around.
まあ おふざけは このくらいで…
What's wrong, Hanekawa?
何があったんだ 羽川
やっぱ あの頭痛か？
Headaches
Animation Number 177
Those headaches again?
Headaches
Animation Number 177
うん
頭痛…は もうないんだけど
Headaches
Animation Number 179
No, I'm feeling better now.
Headaches
Animation Number 179
あの… 阿良々木くん
Araragi-kun... About Golden Week...
ゴールデンウィークのこと… さ
I remembered something.
私 思い出したんだけど
Oh.
そう… なのか
No, it's not that.
いや そうじゃないのかな
I feel like I'm remembering something I forgot.
忘れてることがあるのを
思い出したって感じだね
I see.
そうか…
A cat.
猫… 猫なんだよね
It's a cat.
REMINISCENCE
I remembered that.
そこは思い出した
The cat we buried together.
阿良々木くんと 一緒に
埋めてあげた あの猫
うん そこは思い出した
I remembered it.
But you didn't just call me out here because you remembered it.
（阿良々木）でも 羽川
僕を
こうして呼び出したってことは
思い出したってだけじゃ
ないんだろう？
Yeah.
（羽川）そうよ
Spirits
Animation Number 194
An aberration, huh...
（阿良々木）
怪異(かいい)… か
Yeah.
（羽川）
そう… だから 阿良々木くんには
So I'd like you to show me how to get to Oshino-san's place.
忍野さんの所へ
案内してもらおうと思って
Can you show me the way?
道案内 頼んでもいいかしら
Of course.
（阿良々木）そりゃ もちろん
... Of course. But can I ask you a couple questions first?
もちろんだけど その前に
２〜３質問させてもらっていいか？
（羽川）
え… いいけど なんで？
I guess. Why?
I've been leaning too hard on Oshino to fix aberrations for me.
（阿良々木）
怪異に関しちゃ
忍野に頼りっぱなしだからな
Even if I end up making it his problem,
最終的に丸投げにするにせよ
I want to have a handle on it first.
話の骨子は整理しておかないと
（羽川）
ああ… そうだね
Okay.
Fine, go ahead and ask.
いいよ　じゃあ 何でも聞いて
You said you've had lots of headaches lately. When exactly did they start?
（阿良々木）
頭痛 最近よくある みたいなことを
言ってたけれど
正確には いつごろからなんだ？
Around a month ago.
（羽川）１か月くらい前かな
Yesterday and the day before were both when I was with you,
おとといと昨日 両方
阿良々木くんの前でだったけれど
and I've had them pretty bad at the bookstore and in front of school too.
本屋さんと
学校の正門の所であった頭痛は
実は かなり ひどかったの
You should have told me then!
言えよ そのとき
Sorry.
ごめん
I didn't want to make you worry.
阿良々木くんに
心配かけたくなかったし
Oh well, don't worry about it.
（阿良々木）まあ いいけどさ
So, after Golden Week,
じゃあ
ゴールデンウィークが終わって以来
has anything happened to you involving cats?
猫に関するエピソードってのは
あるのか？
CAT
Animation Number 207
猫に関するエピソード？
Something involving cats?
Even just a black cat crossing your path.
（阿良々木）
黒猫が目の前を横切ったとか
そういうレベルで いいんだけど
May twenty-seventh,
during the radio show
Animation Number 155
On May 27th,
（羽川）
５月27日—
Postcard picture
Animation number 210
Naoetsu city
broadcasting station
To radio program
"Raido late night show"
Nickname
"I love big pandas"
the radio show I listen to at night read a letter from someone named "Big Bear Cat".
夜頃に聴いていたラジオ番組で
A
It may look quite fun in anime
and manga, but being a maid
is a surprisingly tough job.
It's nothing to go "moe-moe"
all over about. In reality,
they don't have time to rest
at all.
Postcard
magnification
ラジオネーム
“大熊猫(おおくまねこ) 大好き”さんの葉書が
読まれていたけれど
Do you think that's related?
それが何か関係あると思う？
（阿良々木）ん… いや ないと思う
No, I don't.
Speaking of which, this is what it said.
ちなみに
葉書の内容は こうだったわ
People in comics and anime seem to have it really easy,
“漫画やアニメなんかでは”
“気楽そうに
もてはやされて いますけれど”
but being a maid must be incredibly stressful work.
“メイドっていうのは
意外と大変な仕事なんですよ”
They don't have any time to rest.
“休む暇なんて
全然ないらしいんですから”
I heard this at a mixer recently, and it's right on the money.
“この間 合コンで会ったときに
聞いたから 間違いありません”
You don't need to go into that much detail.
（阿良々木）
いや
そこまで説明しなくて いいから
By the way, Araragi-kun. Don't you think there was something funny about that letter?
ところで 阿良々木くん
この葉書 何が面白いんだと思う？
I can't quite put my finger on it, though.
私には
ちょっと分からないんだけど
Um... He heard that maids never have any spare time,
（阿良々木）え〜と だから
“メイドは休む暇なんて全然ない”
とか言っておきながら
from someone he met at a relaxed mixer.
ちゃっかり お気楽な合コンに
参加してるじゃん！
That's funny.
て… ところが笑える
Why did you even need to tell me about that letter?!
て… なんで僕が
そんな葉書のフォローを
しなくちゃならねえんだよ！
Oh, I see. I didn't quite get it the first time.
ああ なるほど
でも やっぱり１回 聞いただけじゃ
ちょっと分かりにくいかな
Bear cat
Animation Number 219
Plus, if you think hard about it, a "Big Bear Cat" isn't a cat, it's a panda!
（阿良々木）
そもそも よく考えてみりゃ
“大熊猫”は猫じゃなくて
Panda - Bear cat
Animation Number 219
パンダだろうが！
うん　そういえば そうだね
Oh, you're right.
Anything else?
（阿良々木）ほかには？
（羽川）ん？ ほか？ えっとね…
Anything?
Well... On the same show, there was a guy named "the Posturing Waggler".
Postcard picture
Animation number 222
To radio program
"Raido late night show"
Nickname
"The brandishing personality"
同じ番組で ラジオネーム
“スブリヲスル ソブリ”さん
"Lately, when I've played President with my friends,"
“この間 友達３人とトランプで
大富豪をしていたときの話です”
"after someone deals, one of them keeps saying things."
“カードが配られたあとで
そのうちの１人が言いだしました”
"Things like 'when I was in middle school, 4 was the highest card'."
“あたしの中学校じゃ”
“４がいちばん強いカードだ
っていうルールだったんだけど”
What's funny about this?
これは どこが面白いの？
When I asked whether there was anything else, I didn't mean any more hard-to-understand letters.
いや ほかにはっていうのは
面白さが分かりにくかった葉書は
ほかには なかったか？
って意味で聞いたんじゃねえよ
Plus, about that letter, in President there's all sorts of weird rules
ちなみに その葉書は
大富豪は８切りだったり
都落ちだったり
like "8s go out of turn" or "anyone who's no longer President becomes the Asshole".
ローカルルールが非常に多いから
それを いいことに
The joke is that they pick the best rules for the hand they've drawn.
自分の手元に配られたカードに
都合のいいルールを
でっちあげた友達がいた
っていうのが 笑いどころだ
Oh, I see! I knew you'd get it.
ああ なるほど さすが阿良々木くん
You thanking me for this doesn't make me happy.
こんなことで
感心されても うれしくない
The brandishing personality
Animation Number 225
Also, about the pen name "the Posturing Waggler",
ああ あと〝スブリヲ
スルソブリ〞
っていうラジオネームも
"Posturing" and "Waggler" are written with the same kanji, so it's a bad pun.
THE BRANDISHING PERSONALITY
Animation Number 225
〝素振(すぶ)り〞と
〝素振(そぶ)り〞が
漢字で書いたら
同じだっていう
細かいシャレに
なってるから
あ… でも 阿良々木くん
But not all the letters to the show are that hard to understand.
その番組 分かりにくい葉書ばかり
じゃないんだよ
Postcard picture
Animation number 227
Naoetsu city
broadcasting station
To radio program
"Raido late night show"
Nickname
"Let's walk peeling apples"
Someone named "Walk toward the apple" wrote.
ラジオネーム
“林檎(りんご)をむいて歩こう”さん
"Yesterday a friend and I went to a video rental place."
“先日 友達と２人で
レンタルビデオ店に行きました”
"We wanted to rent the DVDs of a certain serial drama,"
“某連続ドラマのＤＶＤを
借りようとしたのですが”
"but someone else had volume 8 out,"
“全13巻のうち ８巻だけが
ほかの人に借りられていたので”
"so we were only able to watch up to volume 7."
“７巻までしか
借りることが できませんでした”
"My friend said 'volume 7 makes it seem like it ends in 8.'"
“７並べで
８を止められている気分だよ〜”
“と言うと 友達は言いました”
"'The person who has volume 8 out now must be chuckling.'"
“今頃 ８巻を借りてる人は
ほくそ笑んでるんだろうね”
アハハ
"I think the person who rented volume 8 is playing Sevens."
８巻を借りてる人のほうは
“７並べみたいだ”
なんて思ってないって
That's pretty funny, but quit talking about the radio!
（阿良々木）
確かに それは面白い話だけど
ラジオの話は もういいんだよ！
Anyway.
（阿良々木）
まあ ともかく 羽川 次の質問だ
Next question, Hanekawa.
Will you take off your hat?
（阿良々木）
その帽子 脱いでくれるか？
That...  That's not a question, Araragi-kun.
それは…
それは質問じゃないよ
阿良々木くん
（阿良々木）そうだな
Really?
そうだよ
Really.
Hanekawa-sama, let me take your hat.
（阿良々木）
羽川様
帽子をこちらでお預かりします
Araragi-kun.
阿良々木くん
（阿良々木）はい
Yes?
You're making me angry.
怒るよ
（阿良々木）怒れよ
Then be angry.
If you want to be angry, go right ahead.
（阿良々木）
怒りたきゃ いくらでも怒ればいい
I care more about my debt to you than our friendship.
僕にとっては お前との友情よりも
お前に恩返しをすることのほうが
ずっと大事だ
What do you mean, your debt to me?
（羽川）恩返しって…
何のことを言ってるのよ？
Spring break.
（阿良々木）
春休みのことを言ってるんだ
That... But that's...
（羽川）あれは…
でも あんなのやっぱり
Didn't you just save yourself?
それこそ 阿良々木くんが
１人で勝手に助かっただけ…
なんでしょう？
違う
No.
Oshino may say so,
それでも 忍野は
そう言うかもしれないけれど
but I think you saved me.
僕は お前に
助けられたと思っている
I owe you my life.
お前は命の恩人だ
I want to do something for you in return.
（阿良々木）
お前のために何かさせてほしいんだ
If I do, even if you get angry or hate me, I can take it.
その結果だったら
怒られても嫌われても
我慢できるさ
Take it, huh.
我慢ね
That's pretty saucy.
生意気なこと言うじゃない
そうか？
Really?
Coming from you, it's saucy.
阿良々木くんのくせに生意気だぞ
That's something a bully would say.
（阿良々木）
それはガキ大将のセリフだぜ？
I didn't expect to hear it from a star pupil.
優等生の言うようなことじゃない
Yeah.
（羽川）そうね
Don't laugh.
笑わないでよ
（阿良々木）あ…
Are you done yet?
も… もういい？
（阿良々木）あ… ああ うん
Ah, yeah.
THANKS
Animation Number 280
Thanks.
ありがとう
Why are you thanking me?
なんで お礼なのよ
Well... Okay, yeah.
（阿良々木）
けど… うん 分かったよ
It feels like Golden Week again.
やっぱゴールデンウィークの続き
って感じだな
If it's that, we can deal with it.
それならそれで対処のしようがある
Yeah.
（羽川）そう… なんだ
All right.
（阿良々木）
よし　じゃあ
忍野の所に行くとしよう
Let's go to Oshino's.
Don't tell me you're going to complain that doubling up on a bike is against the law?
まさか 羽川
自転車の２人乗りは
法律違反だなんて
そんなこと言わないよな？
I kind of want to, but I'll let it slide.
言いたいところだけれど
見逃してあげる
I made you skip school, so it's fair.
阿良々木くんに学校サボらせたのと
これとでチャラね
Isn't calling that a fair trade kind of weird?
（阿良々木）
いや それでチャラになるのは
おかしくないか？
Both are in your favor
Animation Number 246
（羽川）エヘヘ…
（阿良々木）フフッ
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
All right, get on.
じゃ 後ろに
（阿良々木）では 行くぞ
Let's go.
（阿良々木）
げえ…
Breasts
Animation Number 295
They're soft.
柔らかい…
And big!
そして 大きい！
Araragi-kun.
阿良々木くん
（阿良々木）がっ！
There's something we need to talk about after we get off the bike.
（羽川）
自転車 降りたら話があるからね
（阿良々木）
じゃ… じゃあ 出発します
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
All right, let's get going.
Even still, it must be so much trouble for you.
それにしても大変だよね
阿良々木くんは
You have to take care of so many people.
（羽川）
いろんな人の いろんな面倒
見なくちゃいけなくって
So many people?
（阿良々木）いろんな人？
Like Senjougahara-san, and Mayoi-chan, and Kanbaru-san,
（羽川）
戦場ヶ原さんとか 真宵(まよい)ちゃんとか
神原(かんばる)さんとか
昨日の千石(せんごく)ちゃんとか…
and Sengoku-chan yesterday.
アハハ 女の子ばっかし
They're all girls, huh.
Shut up.
（阿良々木）うるせえよ
And always with aberrations, now that I think of it.
（羽川）
全部 怪異がらみだったんだね
思い出した
（阿良々木）ん…
It seems like you're not done yet.
（羽川）
何だか
まだ中途半端な感じだけど…
That's right.
そうよね　戦場ヶ原さん
There's no way Senjougahara-san really recovered that quickly.
そんな急に
病気 治ったりするわけがないよね
It started when you were attacked by a vampire over spring break.
始まりは 春休みに阿良々木くんが
吸血鬼に襲われたところ… か
Vampire
That's when it all began.
あそこから 全部が始まったんだね
Vampire
Weight crab
The aberrations themselves were always there.
（阿良々木）怪異自体は ずっと
Lost cow
当たり前のように
そこにあるものであって
Lost cow
Monkey's paw
It's not like they just showed up one day.
ある日 突然 現れたわけじゃない
らしいけどな
Monkey's paw
Jagirinawa
Did you know, Araragi-kun?
（羽川）阿良々木くん 知ってる？
Know what?
（阿良々木）知ってるって何を？
One of the special powers of vampires.
（羽川）
吸血鬼の特性の１つなんだけどね
They captivate humans with their charm.
魅了っていって
吸血鬼は人間を虜(とりこ)にしちゃうんだ
Captivate?
（阿良々木）虜？
It's like hypnotism.
（羽川）
催眠術みたいなものなのかな
One gaze into those eyes can captivate someone for life.
その目で見つめることによって
異性を虜にするのよ
ふうん
けれど それが どうした？
So what?
Nothing, just a thought I had.
別に　でも ちょっと思ったの
Senjougahara
Hitagi
Maybe it has something to do
Senjougahara
Hitagi
ここのところ 阿良々木くんが
女の子にモテモテなのは
Senjougahara
Hitagi
Hachikuji
Mayoi
Kanbaru
Suruga
with why you're so popular with the girls all of a sudden.
Sengoku
Nadeko
そういうのも
関係してるのかなあって
Sengoku
Nadeko
Hanekawa
Tsubasa
Sorry, I'm just teasing.
ごめんね
今 私 意地悪なこと言ったよね
Don't worry.
別に　そうでもないだろ
If anything, it helps me understand.
むしろ 納得したくらいだぜ
Charm, huh.
なるほど　魅了ね
You know everything.
お前は何でも知ってるな
I don't know everything.
何でもは知らないわよ
何でもは… 知らないわよ
I don't know anything...
何にも… 知らない
I know nothing at all
Animation Number 321
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Hey, it's Araragi-kun.
（忍野）
おや
阿良々木くんじゃないか
And the class prez, right?
それに 委員長ちゃん… だよね
Her hair's different, but with those glasses it's gotta be her.
髪形は変わってるけど うん
その眼鏡は間違いなく
委員長ちゃんだ
（忍野）
ハハッ 委員長ちゃんは久しぶり
Long time no see, Prez.
Araragi-kun, I saw you yesterday.
阿良々木くんは１日ぶり
ん… あれ？
What, can't you say "I've been waiting" or "I stayed up waiting"?
“待ってたよ”とか
“待ちくたびれたよ”とか
Nothing like that today?
そういうふうなこと
今日は言わないのか？
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Huh? Really?
（忍野）
ああ え？
そうだっけ？
（阿良々木）ん？
What's up, Prez?
委員長ちゃん どうしたんだい？
You have today off?
今日は平日だろう？
I don't really think he's trying to sabotage you.
阿良々木くんなら ともかく
委員長ちゃんが
サボタージュってのは
考えにくいねえ
ハハッ そうか これがあれだ
Oh, that's it?
Must be the Foundation Day I've heard about.
うわさに聞く創立記念日ってやつか
Well, no.
ああ その… 違います
（忍野）ん？ 帽子…
A cap?
That cap looks good on you.
似合うねえ その帽子
はい…
Thanks.
（忍野）ふうん
So that's what you're up to, Araragi-kun?
そういうことかい　阿良々木くん
You really can't even take three steps without getting in trouble.
（忍野）
本当に君は３歩 歩けば
面倒事を引き込んでくるな
ハハッ とりあえず入れよ
Anyway, come on in.
うん 阿良々木くん
To be honest, I'm really busy right now, Araragi-kun.
実を言うと 今は僕
珍しく取り込んでいてね
I'm so busy I don't have any spare time.
忙しくって
あんまり時間が ないんだよ
I see.
そう… なのか？
Oh well, I don't mind.
でも いいよ
You're you, but I've gotta be a bit accomodating if Prez comes to me with a problem.
阿良々木くんなら ともかく
委員長ちゃんの 一大事とくれば
ある程度の融通は利かせるよ フッ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Meddlecat
Animation Number 348
A meddlecat.
障(さわ)り猫(ねこ)
It has to be considered one of the three legendary cat spirits.
怪異ということでいうなら
有名な 三大化け猫伝説には
触れておくべきだろうね
ハハッ いやいや こんなこと
You're you, but I don't even need to tell this to Prez, do I?
阿良々木くんなら ともかく
委員長ちゃんには
言うまでもないことかな？
Hey, stop it with the "You're you, but" when you mention Hanekawa.
おい 羽川のことを言うときに
枕ことばのように
“阿良々木くんなら ともかく”
というのを やめるんだ 忍野
It's starting to get to me.
それ じわじわと効いてくるぞ
I'm not doing it on purpose.
いやあ 僕も わざと
言ってるわけじゃないんだけど
I just can't tell a lie.
真実ってのは
口をついちゃうんだよねえ
You'd better keep your eyes open at night.
（阿良々木）
夜道に気をつけろよ てめえ
Don't worry. I'm a night owl.
心配ご無用 僕は夜行性でね
ハハッ 夜行性というなら
Cats are night owls, too.
猫も そうだっけ？
は… 羽川？
Hanekawa?!
Don't get worked up, Araragi-kun.
（忍野）慌てるなよ 阿良々木くん
It's quite nice.
元気いいなあ
Isn't it a good thing?
何か いいことでも あったのかい？
Getting to see Prez's cat ears,
委員長ちゃんの猫耳が見られたとか
getting to see her in her pajamas,
委員長ちゃんのパジャマ姿が
見られたとか
Don't judge me like that!
お決まりの口癖に
具体的な推測を付け加えるな！
You're misunderstanding!
誤解を招くだろうが！
It's not a misunderstanding, is it?
（忍野）誤解じゃないだろう 別に
If anything, you should thank me for giving you an excuse to bike the whole way here
むしろ 自転車で委員長ちゃんに
抱きつかれていたことに
一切 触れずにやっている僕に
with Prez's arms wrapped around you.
感謝の言葉が
あってもいいくらいだ
（阿良々木）ん…
You've already scouted out the situation, haven't you.
（忍野）
阿良々木くんが 既に事情聴取は
終えていてくれたらしいからね
What happened with the shy girl the day before yesterday must have woken you up.
おとといの照(て)れ屋ちゃんの件は
阿良々木くんにとって
いいパンチだったみたいだね
So Sengoku's a shy girl?
（阿良々木）
千石は照れ屋ちゃんかよ…
Anyway, what's happening?
いや それより 何をしたんだ？
With what you've learned, I don't really have anything to do.
（忍野）
阿良々木くんが
心得てきたおかげで
僕が することは
ほとんど なかったからね
I'm gonna skip a step here.
ちょっと手順を省略した
Skip a step?
（阿良々木）省略？
There's no time, right?
（忍野）時間がないって言ったろ？
And it's quicker to ask her herself than bother Prez.
それに…
委員長ちゃんに話を聞くよりは
本人に話を聞いたほうが
いくらか手っとり早い
Herself?
本人… か
でも…
But...
おっと
Yeah.
ほら もう来たぜ 阿良々木くん
Here she comes, Araragi-kun.
Here comes the sex kitten.
色ぼけ猫のお出ましだ
（阿良々木）ああ！
（ブラック羽川）ニャハハハ〜
So we meet again, human. I'm amazed.
また会えるとは驚いたにゃあ 人間
And it looks like you haven't been punished for lusting after my myaster's boobs.
懲りもせずに
俺のご主人のおっぱいに
欲情しやがったみたいで
You're always such a bad boy, meow.
相変わらず お前はダメダメにゃ
Do you want to be eaten up?
食い殺されたいのかにゃん
Tsubasa Cat, Part Three
Cat
Bakemonogatari
TO BE CONTINUED
（火憐）火憐だぜ！
（月火）月火だよ！
I'm Karen!
I'm Tsukihi!
Hey, about baseball.
（火憐）野球ってさ
（月火）野球ってさ？
About baseball?
You can't question the ump, can you?
（火憐）
審判に文句 言ったら
ダメだと思ってない？
（月火）
ダメじゃないの？
You can't.
The ump's judgments are absolute!
（火憐）
審判は 確かに絶対
The ump's judgments are absolute!
（月火）
審判は 確かに絶対
But you can try to fast-talk him.
（火憐）
でも アピールプレーってのが
あるんだよ
（月火）
アピールプレー？
Fast-talk him?
Hey umpire, don't pretend with me, you had to have seen that was an out.
（火憐）
“いやいや いやいや 審判さん
今のアウトっすよ”
“バックレないで くださいよ
アンタだって見てましたよね？”
Sometimes it works!
って言えばアウトになるケース
（月火）
気さくだね！
Cunning!
If you do it at the wrong time, you get ejected!
（火憐）
使いどころを間違えれば
退場になるぜ！
（月火）
退場不良！
Get outta here, you bum!
Preview quiz!
（火憐）予告編クイズ！
（月火）クイズ！
Quiz!
（火憐）予告編 スクイズ
（月火）スクイズ！
Preview squeeze!
Squeeze?
Squeeze means bunting!
（火憐）
スクイズといえば バントですが
Bunting?
（月火）
バントですが！
What's a safety squeze? I don't get it!
（火憐）
セーフティースクイズって何だよ
意味 分かんね〜よ
I don't get it at all! What's safe about a sacrifice bunt?
いや本当 全然 意味分かんねえ
犠牲バントなのに
なんでセーフティーなんだよ
It's sacrificial! That's a paradox, make up your mind!
全然 犠牲じゃね〜じゃん
矛盾してんじゃんよ
そこんとこ はっきりしろよ
何 曖昧に ごまかそうとしてんだよ
Being so vague makes it confusing! What's with a bunt that makes you safe by sacrificing you?!
“自分も生きようという
犠牲バントですね” なんだそりゃ！
That wasn't a quiz, that was just a complaint!
（月火）
クイズじゃなくて ただの文句！
Next time, Tsubasa Cat part 4!
Next Time
Tsubasa Cat, Part Four
（火憐・月火）
次回「つばさキャット
其ノ肆(そのよん)」
A bunt to advance the runner!
（火憐）
ランナーを あの世に送りバント
A failed bunt.
（月火）
バント 失敗じゃん